Gail Jefferson papers, circa 1960s-2008
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gail Jefferson papers
circa 1960s-2008
2319
UCLA Library Special Collections
14.2 linear feet (35 document boxes and 1 shoe box)
Gail Jefferson (1938-2008) was an internationally renowned scholar in the field of Conversation Analysis, and developed transcription taxonomy standards used in the detailed analysis of conversational exchanges. The collection contains transcripts, talks, reports, articles, drafts, project proposals, news clippings, notes, recordings, and data collections from the major part of Jefferson’s career, which began when she was a student of UCLA Sociologist Harvey Sacks in the 1960s and continued until her death in 2008.
Jefferson, Gail, 1938-2008
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
RESTRICTED MATERIALS: Box 9, Folder 3; Box 10, Folders 1-2, 5, 8-9.
Transcripts with full patient or doctor names were photocopied and names redacted, redacted photocopies were retained in these folders, and the extra set of photocopies used for the creation of redacted copies was shredded. The originals have been retained within the collection file. The originals will replace the redacted copies in 2117.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8092531
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Albert Stuulen, 2014.
Biography/History
Gail Jefferson (1938-2008), a leading scholar of Conversation Analysis, developed transcription standards for use in this field. Jefferson earned her B.A. in Dance at UCLA in 1965 and her Ph.D. in Social Sciences at UC Irvine in 1972. Inspired by Harold Garfinkel's Ethnomethodology, Conversation Analysis was developed by UCLA Sociologist Harvey Sacks along with Jefferson and UCLA Sociology Professor Emanuel Schegloff as co-founders.
Conversation Analysis is an approach to the study of social interaction, embracing both verbal and non-verbal conduct of mundane interactions. Jefferson's work specifically examines overlapping exchanges, laughter, and other interactional phenomena in daily conversation.
In addition to transcribing and editing two published volumes of lectures by UCLA Professor Harvey Sacks, Jefferson published articles and performed transcription for other scholars in the field. She taught Conversation Analysis methods at a summer school in Denmark in the early 2000s, and lived in the Netherlands with her husband Albert Stuulen until her death in 2008.
Talking About Troubles in Conversation, a compilation of Jefferson’s essays edited by Paul Drew, John Heritage, Gene Lerner, and Anita Pomerantz, was published by Oxford University Press in 2015.
Scope and Content
The material covers the major part of Gail Jefferson’s career as a scholar in Conversation Analysis, including transcripts of conversations used for research and workshops, data collections, reports, talks, drafts and completed articles, project proposals, and news clippings. This collection contains transcriptions of UCLA Professor Harvey Sacks' lectures from the 1960s used for Jefferson’s edited volumes of his published work as well as Jefferson's audio cassette and VHS recordings of interviews and conversations, raw material for transcription and analysis.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series based on preservation of the existing order and the imposition of an intellectual order:
1. Offers, Compliments, and Corrections
2. Complete Articles and Corresponding Notes
3. Collections, Notes, and Articles
4. Workshop Materials and Transcripts
5. Harvey Sacks' Lectures and Related Materials
6. Transcripts, Talks, and Collections
7. Project Proposals and Reports
8. "At first I thought" Materials
9. Latency and Poetics Materials
10. Poetics Paper and Standard Max Materials
11. Audiovisual Materials
Conversation Analysis Taxonomy Terms
The terms used to organize series titles are part of a taxonomy developed by Gail Jefferson and Harvey Sacks, and are highly specific to concepts examined in the field of Conversation Analysis. Terms are listed in the order in which they appear in each series, and are also found within the series scope and content notes.
Offers: conversations centered around someone giving/offering information, working through some sort of informational dilemma.
Compliments: conversations commenting on the likeable nature of things/people.
Non corrections: corrections that did not happen in the conversation, Jefferson interpreting potential “corrections” or secondary meanings of what is said, interpreting content. Conversations where people choose not to correct each other, interprets this choice. Examines verbal and mental corrections that could have been made in conversation.
Corrections: information is confirmed in conversation.
Overlap: a recipient starts to talk at a possible end of a turn in progress while the current speaker, instead of stopping there, goes on with more talk.
Question No: questions that end either directly in no, indirect responses suggesting no.
Troubles-telling: type of confessional conversation when a “trouble” or emotional problem is revealed.
Conversation restart: someone starts a new topic to move out of talk about a trouble.
Insertions: different instances including insertions of word particles, word repair, comment on statement, background information, and modifiers.
Topic shift: broadly understood as to shift to new, related, closing, or prior topics. Shifts differ in speaker and emotional severity.
Topic attrition-hold: the topic is not abandoned, but no additional life is contributed to the topic and as a result the topic withers.
Heroic minimizing: invoking the ordinary on the occurrence of the extraordinary. Acting humble/modest in response to a heroic deed.
Mundane Boundarying: mundane talk after a special/problematic event.
I thought: 'At first I thought' A normalizing device for extraordinary events. In Gene H. Lerner (Ed.), Conversation Analysis: Studies from the First Generation (pp.131-167). Philadelphia: John Benjamins, 2004.
Call closings: final or closing talk at the end of a phone call between two people.
Going along with: when people in conversation essentially go along with what is said.
Adjacency pairs: (broadly) some natural two-utterance sequences in which their parts properly go adjacently. A large number of them are known names, and given the names, the parts are relatively ordered and discriminatively related (from lecture 1 folder 1).
‘uh’: when someone initially responds with 'uh' before their actual answer to a question in conversation.
Sequencing in conversation: aims to lay out some of the ways that the discoverable aspects of single utterances turn out to be handleable by reference to sequencing considerations. Examines how sequencing considerations turn out to be implicative of what happens in a given utterance (Sacks).
Latency: delay/silence before a transfer of information.
Stolen Jokes: joke-teller displays recipient-ship of the steal or joke-teller dis-attends the steal (Jefferson).
Pursuit tags: relates to (1981) “The Abominable 'ne?' An Exploration of Post-Response Pursuit of Response.” In P. Shroder (Hrsg.), Sprache der gegenwaart (pp.53-88). Dusseldorf.
Innocuous and Problematic Standard Max: silences in talk.
Related Material
Harold Garfinkel Papers (Collection 1273). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Harvey Sacks Papers (Collection 1678). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Container List
- Offers, Compliments, and Corrections.
  Scope and Content
  BOX 1 TERMS
  Offers: conversations centered around someone giving/offering information, working through some sort of informational dilemma.
  Compliments: conversations commenting on the likeable nature of things/people.
  Non corrections: corrections that did not happen in the conversation, Jefferson interpreting potential “corrections” or secondary meanings of what is said, interpreting content. Conversations where people choose not to correct each other, interprets this choice. Examines verbal and mental corrections that could have been made in conversation.
  Corrections: information is confirmed in conversation.
  Overlap: a recipient starts to talk at a possible end of a turn in progress while the current speaker, instead of stopping there, goes on with more talk.
  Question No: questions that end either directly in no, indirect responses suggesting no.
  - Offers., 2001. (Box 1, Folders 1-2, 6)
    Collection of offers used as the basis for work in Odense Summer School. Folder 2 also contains correspondence with Paul Drew.
  - Compliments., 2000. (Box 1, Folders 3-5)
    Collection of compliments used as the basis for work in Odense Summer School. Folder 4 includes expanded fragments from collection. Folder 5 includes a handout containing fragments and handwritten notes on a candidate phenomenon.
  - Corrections. (Box 24, Folders 1-4, Box 25, Folders 1, 9, Box 1, Folders 7-11)
    Box 1
    Folders 7 and 8: Collection of non-corrections and related practices. Folder 7 includes brief handwritten notes.
    Folder 9: Preliminary list of correction category in which two broad categories present: correction and question no. Each broad category has approximately 20 sub-types.
    Folder 10: Collection of corrections and non-corrections.
    Folder 11: Instances of corrections appearing in overlap.
    Box 24
    Folder 1: Rahman corrections transcripts.
    Folders 2-4: Rahman corrections collection.
    Box 25
    Folder 1: Conference paper and data handouts for “On Exposed and Embedded Correction in Conversation.”
    Folder 9: Drafts, papers, and lectures for “”Embedded Correction: An Interactional Non-Event.”
  - Odense University materials. (Box 26, Folders 1-9)
    Box 26
    Folder 1:Data collections and handouts for Odense Summer School 2003 in Conversation Analysis.
    Folder 2: Schedules, course outlines, and exercises for Odense Summer School 2003 in Conversation Analysis.
    Folders 3: List of participants, pre-assignment materials, and participants work for Odense Summer School 2003 in Conversation Analysis.
    Folders 4: Emails, notes, and participant work for Odense Summer School 2004.
    Folder 5: Data Collection of Apologies for Odense Summer School 2003.
    Folder 6: Data Collection for Odense Summer School 2004.
    Folder 7: Meiji Gakuin collection.
    Folder 8: Materials relating to a research symposium: Conversational analysis of foreign language data, Odense University, Denmark, 1994.
    Folder 9: Papers on from other academics in Ethnomethodology and Conversation Analysis sent to Jefferson for editorial revision.
- Complete Articles and Corresponding Notes.
  BOX 2 TERMS
  Troubles-telling: type of confessional conversation when a “trouble” or emotional problem is revealed.
  Conversation restart: someone starts a new topic to move out of talk about a trouble.
  - Transcripts. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Two transcripts “Where’ve you been” and “Yer line’s been busy” prepared for a data session.
  - Articles. (Box 2, Folders 2-3, 5, 10-11)
    Folder 2: Complete Stepwise Transitions articles.
    Folder 3: Two complete copies of article ‘What’s in a “Nyem.’”
    Folder 5: Complete articles “On ‘Trouble-Premonitory’ Response to Inquiry” and “On The Organization of Laughter in Talk About Troubles.”
    Folder 10: Copy of article “List-Construction as a Task and Resource” as first presented in 1973, published in 1991.
    Folder 11: Copies of article “List-Construction as a Task and Resource,” copies are dated 1980-referring to the First British/German Conference on Ethnomethodology and Conversational Analysis at the University of Konstanz, 1980.
  - Paper., 1982. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Complete paper Jefferson delivered on selective detailing/glossing and corresponding notes from a University of Manchester class.
  - Conference packet. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Jefferson's annotated Centro Internazionale Di Semiotica E Linguistica Urbino, Italy conference packet.
  - Lectures. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Two versions of lecture on Error-Correction (what Jefferson was then calling Mistake-Correction format).
  - Reports., 1978-1980. (Box 2, Folders 8-9)
    Folder 8: Progress and end reports on project “The Analysis of Conversation in which ‘Troubles’ and “Anxieties’ are Expressed” to Social Science Research Council.
    Folder 9: Complete final report on project “The Analysis of Conversation in which ‘Troubles’ and “Anxieties’ are Expressed” to Social Science Research Council conducted with J. Lee, University of Manchester.
  - Bibliographies., 1965, circa 1980. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Different versions of Conversation Analysis bibliography. This folder also includes a bibliography of Harvey Sacks’ published and unpublished work, a Sacks handout detailing an exam from Spring 1965, and a glossary of transcript symbols.
- Collections, Notes, and Articles.
  BOX 3 TERMS
  Insertions: different instances including insertions of word particles, word repair, comment on statement, background information, and modifiers.
  Topic shift: broadly understood as to shift to new, related, closing, or prior topics. Shifts differ in speaker and emotional severity.
  Topic attrition-hold: the topic is not abandoned, but no additional life is contributed to the topic and as a result the topic withers.
  Heroic minimizing: invoking the ordinary on the occurrence of the extraordinary. Acting humble/modest in response to a heroic deed.
  BOX 4 TERMS
  Mundane Boundarying: mundane talk after a special/problematic event.
  BOX 5 TERMS
  I thought: "'At first I thought' A normalizing Device for Extraordinary Events." In Gene H. Lerner (Ed.) Conversation Analysis: Studies from the First Generation (pp.131-167). Philadelphia: John Benjamins, 2004.
  Call closings: final or closing talk at the end of a phone call between two people.
  - Collections. (Box 4, Folders 3, 9-11, Box 29, Folders 3-4, Box 3, Folders 1-5, 9, 12-13, Box 5, Folders 2, 5, 8, 10-11, Box 17, Folder 2)
    Box 3
    Folder 1: Collection of insertions data.
    Folder 2: Collection of assessments.
    Folder 3: Collections related to topic shifts.
    Folder 4: Collection of topic attrition-hold and topic shifts.
    Folder 5: A collection of “Yeah yeahs” selected from Jefferson/Lee Troubles Talk collection.
    Folder 9: Collection of compliments data.
    Folder 12: Collection of newspaper clippings related to heroic acts and notes on ‘heroic minimizing.’
    Folder 13: A Collection of 37 call openings sent to Jefferson by Emanuel Schegloff.
    Box 4
    Folder 3: Collection of data for “Remarks on the Post-Self-Correction Repeat” and assorted handwritten notes to self.
    Folder 9: Collection exploring problem of pseudonyms. Also includes papers titled “A Report on Some Difficulties Encountered when Using Pseudonyms in ‘Research Generative’ Transcripts” and “Some Notes on Pseudonyms.”
    Folder 10: This collection of data in which arrangements are being made was sent to Jefferson by Paul Drew.
    Folder 11: Assortment of small collections. Folder also contains transcripts and notes.
    Box 5
    Folder 2: Collection of "I thought."
    Folder 5: Collection of news receipts dated February 1980. Folder also includes handwritten copy of collection.
    Folder 8: Collection of “Because” in Overlap which Jefferson puts in parentheses: From Conjunctionals Collections.
    Folder 10: Collection of call closings.
    Folder 11: Collection of data in which participants argue.
    Box 17
    Folder 2: Collections from Mrs. P.B which include corrections.
    Box 29
    Folders 3-4: Collection of Sudnow conversations which Jefferson titled "The Ladies."
  - Articles. (Box 4, Folders 1, 6, Box 3, Folders 6-8, 10, Box 6, Folders 1-3, 6, 10, Box 5, Folders 6, 9)
    Folder 6: Proofs for (2002) “Is 'No' an acknowledgment token? Comparing American and British uses of (+)/(-) tokens.” Journal of Pragmatics, 34, 1345-1383.
    Folder 7: Copy of article “On Exposed and Embedded Correction in Conversation.”
    Folder 8: Draft and proofs for 2004 “A Note on Laughter in ‘Male-Female’ Interaction.”
    Folder 10: Editor’s proofing symbols.
    Folder 1: Proofs of “Preliminary notes on abdicated other-correction.” This folder also includes handout and notes on Post-Self-Correction Repeat.
    Folder 6: Copy of “Remarks on the Post-Self-Correction Repeat.” This folder also includes a data session handout related to this article and annotated copy of Emanuel Schegloff’s talk titled “Discourse As An Interactional Achievement II: An Exercise In Conversation Analysis.”
    Folder 6: Proofs and letters relating to “A Note on Resolving Ambiguity.”
    Folder 9: Early and rewritten versions of “Is “No” an Acknowledgement Token? Comparing American and British Use of (+) – (-) Tokens.”
    Box 6
    Folder 1: Copies of “A Technique for Inviting Laughter and its subsequent Acceptance/Declination.” Folder 2: Copies of article, lectures, and handouts for “Notes on ‘Latency’ in Overlap Onset.”
    Folder 3: Copy of “Notes on Laughter in the Pursuit of Intimacy” published with Sacks and Schegloff, 1987.
    Folder 6: rafts, final copies, and published version of University of Manchester Sociology paper No. 6 “The Abominable ‘Ne?’: A Working Paper Exploring The Phenomenon of Post-Response Pursuit of Response,” April 1981.
    Folder 10: Copy of “On the Poetics of Ordinary Talk” published in Text and Performance Quarterly, January 1996.
  - Papers. (Box 3, Folder 11, Box 6, Folder 7, Box 5, Folder 1, Box 25, Folders 3, 7)
    Box 3: Complete paper “Sketch! Some Orderly Aspects of Overlap in Natural Conversation,” presented with Emanuel Schegloff as second author, December 1975.
    Box 5: Paper titled “Some Notes on Pseudonyms.”
    Box 6: Copy of paper “On the interactional unpackaging of a ‘gloss’” sent to Language in Society. Folder includes correspondence with editors from 1984-1985.
    Folder 3: Copies of paper “Notes on Some Orderlinesses of Overlap Onset,” presented at University of Lancaster, March 1984.
    Folder 7: Notes and data for paper “Another Failed Hypothesis: Pitch/Loudness and Overlap Resolution.”
  - Lectures. (Box 6, Folders 4-5, 8-9, Box 5, Folders 3-4, 7, Box 4, Folders 2, 5, 8, Box 25, Folder 2)
    Folder 2: Two incomplete copies of “Remarks on the Post-Self-Correction Repeat” given at Copenhagen, 2002.
    Folder 5: Talk titled “Colligation as a Device for Minimizing Repair or Disagreement” presented at “Talk and Social Structure,” University of California, Santa Barbara, March 1986.
    Folder 8: Talk titled “Managing Extraordinary Events: II” and collection of extractions and notes on mundane boundarying.
    Folder 3: Copies of talk “Notes on a Systematic Deployment of the Acknowledgement Tokens 'Yeah' and 'Mm hm'” 1983 revisited 1999. Folder includes a handout relating to talk.
    Folder 4: Copies of talk and corresponding data handouts for “Is 'No' an Acknowledgement Token? Comparing American and British Use of (+) – (-) Tokens” given at Jyvaskyla, August 1996. Folder includes an abstract from the conference with a note from Paul Drew on back.
    Folder 7: Copy of a lecture and corresponding handouts for “Remarks on ‘Non-Correction’ in Conversation.”
    Folder 4: Copies of talk and paper “An Exercise in the Transcription and Analysis of Laughter.”
    Folder 5: Talk titled “Preliminary Notes on the Sequential Organization of Laughter” given in 1973 with Sacks and Schegloff.
    Folder 8: Talk titled “On Exposed and Embedded Correction in Conversation” and corresponding data handout.
    Folder 9: Copies of two talks and corresponding data handouts for “The Rejection of Advice: Managing the Problematic Convergence of a ‘Troubles-Telling’ and a ‘Service Encounter’” given with John R. E. Lee and “On a Problematic Convergence: ‘Telling a Trouble’ and/or ‘Negotiating a Plan.’” Folder also includes paper titled “The Rejection of Advice: Managing the Problematic Convergence of a Troubles-Telling and a Service Encounter.”
    Folder 2: Handouts and data for lecture on transcribing “Caricature versus Detail.”
  - Notes. (Box 25, Folders 4, 6, Box 4, Folder 4)
    Folder 4: Notes and handout for talk “On counting cases for a distributional analysis.”
    Folder 4: Notes and data handout on overlap.
    Folder 6: Notes and handouts for “Issues for Transcription.”
- Workshop Materials and Transcripts.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing.
  BOX 25 TERM
  Going along with: when people in conversation essentially go along with what is said.
  - Workshop materials. (Box 22, Folder 1, Box 7, Folders 1-8, Box 17, Folder 5)
    One 3.5 inch floppy disk.
    BOX 7: FOLDER 5 CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing.
    Box 7
    Folder 1: Participants’ pre-assignments, marked by Jefferson, for Conversation Analysis Seminar 2006 at Meiji Gakuin University.
    Folder 2: Email from an Acquisitions Editor at Wiley Blackwell dated May 31, 2007.
    Folder 3: Copies of talk “Colligation as a Device for Minimizing Repair or Disagreement.” One copy originally presented at UCSB in 1986 but revised for workshop presentation in Tokyo, March 2006 and other copy revised in September 2006.
    Folder 4: Emails between Jefferson and Gene Lerner, Aug Nishizaka, and Paul Drew concerning arrangements for Tokyo workshops in Japan. This folder includes two copies of Debbie and Shelley transcript for workshop.
    Folder 5: Email from Paul Drew attaching collection of offers from Holt corpus plus a list of transcription changes. This folder includes a floppy disk of this collection and additional emails and letters between Jefferson and Drew.
    Folder 6: Papers and notes relating to transcripts and participants for Tokyo workshop, 2005.
    Folder 7: Transcript for London data sessions.
    Folder 8: Collection of Doctor Patient transcripts related to workshops in conjunction with Drew.
    Folder 5: Receipts and letters relating to Sixth International Systemic-Functional Workshop, University of Antwerp, 1994.
    Box 22
    Folder 1: Programs and papers for Discourse Analytic Research Weeks: Medical and Therapeutic Communication, 1987.
  - Transcripts. (Boxes 9-10, Box 8, Folders 1-5, Box 25, Folders 5, 8)
    Box 8
    Folder 1: Transcripts from preliminary hearing of O.J. Simpson trial and coverage of trial from television shows such as Larry King Live, CNN, and BBC2.
    Folder 2: Transcripts from Rivera Live “Black Rage: Abuse Excuse?” May 16, 1994 and Larry King Live March 17, 1995. Folder also includes Dutch transcript, Alle Mensen Zijn Ongelijk.
    Folder 3: Verbatim record of Biography of Edward VIII, undated. Folder includes copy of record with notes.
    Folder 4: Transcripts of excerpts from television shows Rivera Live and Larry King Live, circa 1990s.